<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second view of the Army remonstrance. Or Justice done to the Armie. Wherein their principles are new model'd, brought out of obscurity into clearer light. By which the Army and the whole kingdome are under the conduct of the spirit of God, led out of a wildernesse to the view of a Canaan. / Dedicated to the Generall, and the Councel of War. By William Sedgwick.</title>
            <author>Sedgwick, William, 1609 or 10-1669?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2389</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E477_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203531</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863468</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863468</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115670</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92865)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115670)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 76:E477[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second view of the Army remonstrance. Or Justice done to the Armie. Wherein their principles are new model'd, brought out of obscurity into clearer light. By which the Army and the whole kingdome are under the conduct of the spirit of God, led out of a wildernesse to the view of a Canaan. / Dedicated to the Generall, and the Councel of War. By William Sedgwick.</title>
                  <author>Sedgwick, William, 1609 or 10-1669?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Hils, and G. Calvert, and are to be sold at his house over against S. Thomases Hospitall in Southwark, and at the Black Spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls, neare Ludgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLIX. [1649, i.e. 1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: A remonstrance of His Excellency Thomas Lord Fairfax, Lord General of the Parliaments forces. And of the generall councell of officers held at St Albans the 16. of November, 1648.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec: 23"; "1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army. --  Council. --  Remonstrance of His Excellency Thomas Lord Fairfax, Lord General of the Parliaments forces. And of the generall councell of officers held at St Albans the 16. of November, 1648.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115670:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A ſecond view of the Army REMONSTRANCE. OR <hi>Juſtice done to the Armie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein</hi> Their Principles are new model'd, brought out of obſcurity into clearer light.</p>
            <p>BY Which the Army and the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome are under the conduct of the Spirit of God, led out of a Wilderneſſe to the view of a <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dedicated To the Generall, and the Councel of War.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Sedgwick.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>In the place where it was ſaid unto them, Ye are not my people, there it ſhall be ſaid unto them, ye are the ſons of the living God,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Hoſe. 1. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Hils,</hi> and <hi>G. Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at his houſe over againſt S. <hi>Thomaſes</hi> Hoſpitall in <hi>Southwark,</hi> and at the Black <hi>Spread-Eagle</hi> at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> neare <hi>Ludgate.</hi> M.DC.XLIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115670:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115670:2"/>
            <head>TO His Excellency <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> GENERALL <hi>Of the Parliaments Forces,</hi> AND To the Generall Councell of Warre.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Have done <hi>Juſtice upon</hi> you becauſe I ſaw evill in you; There is a holy One likewiſe in you, I <hi>muſt doe him Juſtice too;</hi> I have ſmitten you, and not you onely, but <hi>the Judge of</hi> Iſrael <hi>with a rod upon the cheeke: It pleaſes me to bruiſe him,</hi> and him as much to be bruiſed; tis his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and therefore he freely ſubmits himſelfe to be <hi>chaſtiſed:</hi> Ephraim <hi>is my dear ſon, a pleaſant childe, For ſince I ſpake againſt him, I doe earneſtly remember him ſtill; Therefore my bowels are troubled for him, I will ſurely have mercy upon him, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It grieves me to ſee you as a <hi>Woman with childe,</hi> big with justice, righteouſneſſe, reformation, &amp;c. and know not how or which way to be delivered: Here is an arm stretched out to you that will <hi>gently leade them that are with young,</hi> and <hi>guide the blind into a way they know not.</hi> You have high and great deſigns, but are impriſon'd in the darkneſſe of fleſh that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get out into a clear and ſtrait way; My intent is to open the two-leav'd gates and free you. I have opened the <hi>left</hi> alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſo turned aſide that dark and evill ſpirit that lay in your way; &amp; ſhal now unfold the <hi>right,</hi> which brings you into light, and ſo <hi>makes crooked places ſtrait for you, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115670:3"/>
            <p>You are upon the execution of juſtice, I would not have you goe blindly, paſſionately and raſhly upon it; but accept this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing of God prepared for you, which will fill you with wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and righteouſneſſe. Aſcend this <hi>Throne of majeſty</hi> firſt, that is here ſet up for you: Ariſe from the common and darke nature of <hi>man</hi> into the holy nature of <hi>God,</hi> and then you will be <hi>able to judge;</hi> ſuffer this holy child Jeſus to come forth, and then goe on in <hi>the name of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reade it, and if you ſee a little truth in it, <hi>reade</hi> it againe; the light is dim, but tis a <hi>morning and growing</hi> light, and wil ſhine <hi>more and more untill perfect day.</hi> This I dare challenge of you from that great and publique truſt that is committed to you, in which we have all a deepe ſhare, from thoſe high and weighty affaires that you are upon, of ſuch mighty concernment to the glory of God, and the good of his people, from that inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity and freeneſſe that you have profeſſed to receive adviſe <hi>from all,</hi> and to give ſatisfaction <hi>to all,</hi> and eſpecially upon the authority of him whoſe name I here declare and ſet up, that you will not ſleight what is offered to you, and lay it aſide unconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; but that you will give it due hearing And if in any thing you diſſent from it, I may know it, and either receive or give ſatisfaction; or if it be doubtfull to you, I may have opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to clear it; or if theſe things appeare true (as I believe they will) but yet at a diſtance from you, that I may by removing that out of the way that hinders you from fellowſhip with them, bring you into the power and poſſeſſion of them; And to this end <hi>I am,</hi> and would be more.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours,</hi> W. Sedgwick.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115670:3"/>
            <head>Juſtice done to the Army <hi>REMONSTRANCE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Told you when I was adminiſtring <hi>Juſtice upon your Remonſtrance,</hi> that it was a mixt thing of good and evill; that the <hi>Lord was in it,</hi> but hid under <hi>ſo much filth</hi> that we could not diſcerne him. You are <hi>Sion,</hi> but not perfect, and therefore we muſt <hi>waſh away your filth and purge away your bloud by the ſpirit of judgement and the ſpirit of burning:</hi> The Lord is amongſt us, <hi>and ſits as a refiner and purifier of ſilver;</hi> he is <hi>ſet</hi> to it cloſe, and will make it his conſtant buſineſſe, and doe it hotly, ſharply; even <hi>the ſilver, the ſons of Levi,</hi> the people of God, muſt paſſe thorow this ſire; and therefore <hi>Who may abide the day of his coming, and who may ſtand when he appeareth?</hi> Many cannot ſtand before it, but are overturnd into a beaſtly ditch of rage, fretting and fooliſh paſſion; this is <hi>a baſtard</hi> ſpirit that cannot <hi>endure chaſtiſement:</hi> But others doe ſtand in peace and quietneſſe, there we ſee the ſpirit and ſtrength of the Son, who willingly <hi>ſuffers chastiſement,</hi> knowing that <hi>he is choſen in the furnace,</hi> and that by it he is made <hi>partaker of Gods holineſſe;</hi> purified from <hi>humane holineſſe,</hi> which is at beſt but filthineſſe, into the <hi>divine holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> And to ſuch I apply that of <hi>Solomon, As the fining pot for ſilver, and the furnace for gold, ſo is a man to his praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>fining pot</hi> and <hi>furnace</hi> are for the beſt mettals, and <hi>tis for their praiſe,</hi> that they may be brought forth in a more noble forme, and fitted to receive ſome excellent impreſſion.</p>
            <p>Now therefore having caſt you into the fire, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away your droſſe, wee ſhall hold you forth with a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115670:4"/>beautiful ſtamp of the majeſty of God upon you: That vail of an uncleane ſpirit being rent away, we now behold your face ſhining with the glory of God upon you; <hi>Now we have taken away the ſcum, and caſt it into the fire,</hi> we may ſafely eate of the meat, having done <hi>justice upon</hi> the fleſhly, worldly part, we muſt doe <hi>juſtice to</hi> the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and holy part.</p>
            <p>The Remonſtrance of it ſelfe is as <hi>the earth, without form and void,</hi> there is a <hi>face</hi> on it, but <hi>tis deep, and darkneſſe is upon it: But the ſpirit of God moving,</hi> or brooding, <hi>upon the face of the Waters,</hi> brings forth a new creation, which is bleſſed and good.</p>
            <p>The Kingdomes of the earth, and the way of Gods dealing with them in theſe laſt times, are deſcrib'd in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> and his Viſion, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. A Kingdome is a great <hi>tree</hi> growing out of the earth unto a great ſtrength and height, <hi>reaching unto heaven, and the ſight thereof unto the ends of the earth;</hi> it grows out of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and receives its life and nouriſhment from the loweſt element the inferiour people, but ariſes up to ſuch a height as touches hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>i. e.</hi> comes near the heavenly glory, the Kingdome of heaven or Chriſt; This tree hath <hi>fair leaves and much fruit, meat for all;</hi> it brings forth honour, order, peace, juſtice, love, riches, advantage to all; Kingdomes afford a univerſall benefit: <hi>The beaſts of the field have ſhadow under it, and the fowles of the heaven dwell in the boughs thereof, &amp; all fleſh feed of it:</hi> All ſorts of men receive protection from it; thoſe that labour and toil as beaſts in the earth, they enjoy their wealth and ſafety under it; and thoſe that fly in the aire of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, learning, they make their neſts of honour and preferment in it, and all live upon it: Or the <hi>beaſts,</hi> men of earthy and civill employment; <hi>Fowles of heaven,</hi> men of religious and heavenly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, all have their peace in this Tree.</p>
            <p>But behold <hi>a watcher, and an holy one came downe from heaven;</hi> This <hi>watcher</hi> is the <hi>watchman of Iſrael,</hi> that keeps us and looks to us while we ſleep; or that <hi>thiefe that comes in the night,</hi> ſecretly ſtealing in upon us while we ſee him not; <hi>and a holy one,</hi> though <hi>a thiefe,</hi> and <hi>in the night breaking downe the houſe,</hi> yet a holy Child Jeſus, a holy Lamb, and we may know who he is, <hi>he came down from heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis the coming of Chriſt from heaven that doth this, <hi>He cryed aloud, and ſaid thus, Hew down the tree, and cut off his branches, ſhake off his leaves, and ſcatter his fruit, let the beaſts get away from under it, and the fowles from his branches:</hi> Heres harſh, cruel doings from one that comes from heaven; <hi>Cryes aloud,</hi> tis not the ſtill voice; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115670:4"/>but deſtruction; <hi>Hew down the tree,</hi> lay the <hi>ax to the root;</hi> cut down all government, dominion, King, Parliament, with all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, order; <hi>cut off the branches</hi> of lawes, offices, places; <hi>Scatter the fruit,</hi> let there be no ſafety, peace, getting of eſtates; <hi>Let the beaſts get from under it, and the fowles from the branches;</hi> let the inhabitants be ſcattered, let wealth be removed, let honour and preferments ceaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nevertheleſſe leave the ſtump of the roots in the earth, with a band of iron and braſſe in the tender graſſe of the field, and let it be wet with the dew of heaven, and let his portion be with the beasts in the graſſe of the earth; let his heart be changed from man, and a beasts heart be given unto him, and let ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times paſse over him;</hi> There is not utter deſtruction, though the glory, honour, riches, peace of the Kingdome be cut down, yet it remaines in the ſtump, <hi>and is ſure</hi> there: Theres nothing left but the <hi>ſtump of the roots in the earth,</hi> ſome life in the loweſt people, and that bound down, yet ſafe kept by <hi>a band of iron and braſse,</hi> by the power of the ſword: <hi>In the tender graſſe of the field,</hi> in the wide field, not in a ſetled, built City, rather a wilderneſſe, amongſt ſome weake, <hi>tender</hi> ſpirits, ſome ſmal <hi>blades</hi> of graſſe that are grown up: <hi>And wet with the dew of heaven,</hi> lying open to heaven in the night of darkneſſe, expecting continual dews of favours and providence; Tis a deſolate and poore condition though it hath a bleſſing in it; they that are gathered into the City of God live better: <hi>Let his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be with the beaſts, let him eate graſſe as the ex;</hi> It is not the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one man onely, but of the whole tree, the ſpirit of domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the Kingdome is <hi>changed from man to beaſt; driven from men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man is a wiſe, lordly creature, that exerciſes dominion by wiſedome and underſtanding, and is inveſted with majeſty, which is honoured and reverenced by others: The new man is the Lord from heaven, living in the light and underſtanding of God, and of excellent goodneſſe and righteouſneſſe; and is therefore honoured becauſe he is the true and great Lord of al, and doth good to al, exerciſing <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> in wiſedome to al; ſuch a heart now appears not amongſt us in no ſort of men, but a <hi>beaſts heart,</hi> rage, violence, fierceneſſe, exerciſe of force one to another, compulſion, driving in herds; not wiſedome to compoſe al into one body; <hi>Theſe eate graſſe as oxen,</hi> live, as oxen, a laborious, traveling, painful life, without any ſetled reſt: <hi>And eate graſſe: All fleſh is graſſe;</hi> the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and beſt men feed upon what providence daily brings for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115670:5"/>them, and that of a fleſhly, fading, dying nature: Not upon the <hi>living bread that comes down from heaven;</hi> not upon the <hi>fatted Calfe</hi> kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and offered up; not on meat roſted by the <hi>everlaſting fire;</hi> not eating the ſpice nor drinking the wine of the <hi>Spirit;</hi> and this <hi>till ſeven times paſſe over thee:</hi> Till the compleat meaſure of Gods ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice paſſe over: which I would gladly reſtrain to ſeven yeares. This is the ſtate of this miſerable Kingdome.</p>
            <p>The intent of God in this which is ſure and <hi>decreed, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand by the word of the holy one;</hi> Tis required and ſhall be effected; <hi>That the living may know,</hi> Firſt, <hi>That the moſt high ruleth in the Kingdome of men;</hi> God will make you all know that himſelfe, <hi>the moſt high,</hi> not a miniſter or angel of his, not a vicegerent, not a civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate only, but the <hi>high</hi> God, the higheſt glory of God <hi>ruleth,</hi> not only over, but <hi>in the Kingdome of men:</hi> This, beaſtly ignorant man knows not, but you muſt know it, though you oppoſe it; and would uphold an earthly Kingdome in which men may rule without God; no, the Lord himſelfe and his moſt high excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſhall rule and be known to rule.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>And giveth it to whomſoever he will:</hi> He rules not in an abſtracted ſenſe without us; but he gives it to whom he pleaſes, will beſtow it upon men; adminiſter this Kingdome in his <hi>higheſt glory</hi> in men: And in beſtowing of it, will not be bound to any perſon or family, as <hi>King,</hi> nor to any ſociety or company of men, as Parliament, nor to any form or cuſtome of men, but when he pleaſeth; will <hi>pull down</hi> ſome, and <hi>exalt</hi> others; will not be fixt upon this or that perſon or thing; but walke up and down with it at his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, <hi>ſetteth up over it the baſeſt of men:</hi> will not leave till he ſet the bottome upon the top, advanced the <hi>baſeſt,</hi> mean, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort of men, men of baſeſt account, of loweſt, ſmalleſt worth not renownd either for honour, riches, learning, wiſdome or any other excellency; but ſet up men of baſe ignoble birth, baſe ſpirits <hi>&amp;c.</hi> over it.</p>
            <p>Theſe three things hath the majeſty of God written out clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in theſe times; the moſt <hi>high ruleth in this Kingdome;</hi> and firſt gave it to the King, but he did not know the <hi>Lord</hi> that gave him his dominion, power and glory; nor govern his People in the goodnes, ſtrength and light of GOD, but ſerved and pleaſed himſelfe by it: and ſo abuſed that rule and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority that God gave, to tyranny, covetuouſneſſe, oppreſſion, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115670:5"/>to ſelf-pleaſure and honour: for this the Lord blaſted his Majeſty, curſed his government, rent his Kingdome and fild it with trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and diſtractions, and forced him againſt his will to call a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, which was virtually, or in a kinde a reſignation of his dominion into their hands: For his great deſigne before was to rule without them, &amp; to uphold his owne intereſt in oppoſition to theirs, looking upon them not as a help to him, but as enemies to his prerogative, being ſet upon principles of government in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety to the Parliament; and his calling them being not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or voluntary, but forced (the union being firſt violated by his diſ-affecting and diſdaining them) it was an erecting or ſetting up another power diſtinct and divided from his owne; and by that God paſſed from him to the Parliament, left him, and ſet up <hi>maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, power</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> in the Parliament, and gave <hi>hearts, affections, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, riches</hi> &amp; <hi>ſtrength</hi> into their hands, and ſo ſeated <hi>himſelf</hi> amongſt them.</p>
            <p>They as ignorant of God as he, and not exalting the <hi>name of God</hi> that gave them their power, but ſeeking their owne and a worldly good, divided from the <hi>Moſt High,</hi> they corrupt likewiſe; And God finding no ſatisfaction or reſt amongſt them, blaſts and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their glory, and fils the Kingdome with ſuch wrath; or rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſuch ſtormes in the nation, that they could not guide the ſhip, but are forced to caſt themſelves, and the government and ſafety of themſelves and Kingdome upon others: Not being able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their owne and the peoples good, they let all fall upon the <hi>people,</hi> and doe expreſly in their declarations appeale to the <hi>people to judge,</hi> and require them to defend their owne ſafety; and upon that ground ſummon them to armes, or raiſe an Army; as may appeare in their Declarations at the beginning of theſe troubles; and thus they erect and ſet up another power, The Army.</p>
            <p>Now it is exactly to be obſerved how ſecretly God paſſes out of one forme into another, as from King to Parliament, and from Parliament to the Army; and not ſo ſecretly, but his footſteps are ſeene viſibly upon and in the actions of men, and he rides his jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney upon their backs. This very much concernes the clearing up of the Armies caſe, and the ſcattering the miſts that yet cover them and hinder them from ſeeing their owne right, and others from diſcerning and acknowledging their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115670:6"/>power; and therefore I ſhall endeavour to unfold it in theſe five particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That there is a tranſmitting or tranſlating of power from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the People, or Army.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That this change of power from Parliament to people is according to humane and divine reaſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>That this power of the People ſo raiſd by the Parliament, is a ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and ſtronger power then that of the Parliament.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>That this Army is truly the people of the Kingdome, already formd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a body of an Army.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>That this forme of an Army is the moſt excellent, agreeable to God, and fitteſt for the preſent worke, and the mother of other powers.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, The Parliament having all power by the preſence of God with them, and the majeſty of the King dying into them; they doe, by the will of God, convey all that they had to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple gathered together in armes for their owne ſecurity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They themſelves ceaſe and expire, their end ceaſing. The end of a Parliament is the execution of juſtice, reforming of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, preſerving the peoples liberties, &amp;c. Now 'twas mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the malignancy of the Kingdome was ſuch, as they could not heal it, and their liberties ſo endangerd they could not ſave them, 'twas beyond their power and skil: And ſo becoming uſeleſſe, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render to others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides they raiſe up another power that is inconſiſtent with their owne; for civil, legal or Parliamentary power cannot ſubſiſt together in the ſame Kingdome with military; but the military wil, and neceſſarily muſt, ſilence, enforce and ſubject the other at his pleaſure. The power of the ſword in a forrain na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be inordinate, but at home, being raiſd for its own ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, 'twil be maſter, and eate up, or trample upon the other.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As an Army, being <hi>rough,</hi> thruſts out the civil power, being the <hi>gentler,</hi> ſo the <hi>people</hi> being raiſd, aboliſhes the <hi>repreſentatives;</hi> for the <hi>figure</hi> or <hi>image</hi> ceaſes when the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> comes in place, it lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes its uſe and imployment when the body it ſelf appeares.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The raiſing of the power of an Army is an act of God, who is the Lord of hoaſts, and hath a peculiar prerogative in gathering them together, and delights much to ſhew himſelfe in this forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115670:6"/>the Parliament were but inſtruments, God the main in raiſing an Army for his owne great deſignes; and therefore as ſoone as theſe are ſet up, he begins to ſhew forth his glory in them, and to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw himſelfe from the other; leaves the Parliament to weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, diviſions, vanities, diſgrace, and appeares in the Army in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſucceſſe, power, vigour: The Parliament ſince the Army was on foot could doe nothing that had the face of <hi>majeſty, juſtice</hi> or <hi>goodneſſe:</hi> On the other ſide the Army goe on with <hi>great honour and glory</hi> in their work, being as full of power as the other empty.</p>
            <p>The Parliament doing nothing ſutable to their truſt, or worthy of a Parliament, the Army diſcharge their place, gallantly, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and happily: So that we ſee the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath <hi>expowerd</hi> it ſelfe and <hi>impowerd</hi> the <hi>people, emptied</hi> and made <hi>void</hi> themſelves of authority, and fild and formd the people with it; and that there is a <hi>tranſition</hi> of the glory of God from one to the other, and ſo a <hi>tranſlation of dominion</hi> from the Parliament the <hi>repreſentative,</hi> to the <hi>body</hi> of the <hi>people,</hi> themſelves.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We muſt know this, that this deſcent of power is moſt <hi>naturall</hi> and according to the will of God, or agreeable to <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> and <hi>divine</hi> reaſon: It is indeed very harſh and unpleaſing to thoſe <hi>beaſts and fowles</hi> that live under the <hi>ſhadow</hi> and <hi>in the branches</hi> of this great <hi>tree</hi> of the Kingdome, and had their intereſt and ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in royalty, in offices, in preferments, &amp;c. It ſeemes to them nothing but confuſion, that all this glory, and with it their lives, ſhould goe into the earth, and remain in <hi>a ſtump of the root;</hi> but if they had the wiſedome of God, and did ſee his counſel and end in it, they would be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>For 1. Tis exceeding natural that when the <hi>ſap</hi> of the tree hath riſen to its height, and brought forth its <hi>fruit,</hi> it ſhould, when the <hi>fruit</hi> fals, and the winter comes, ſharp and cold ſeaſons, return into its <hi>root.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Power did ariſe from <hi>ſimple, poore man,</hi> had its originall from the duſt of the earth, <hi>common people,</hi> and receives its life and being from <hi>humane nature</hi> in its ſimple ſtate; there it was pureſt, unmixt from pride, cruelty, deceit, it was quieteſt and at reſt without violence and diſturbance, though in a mean and rude manner: And thence it riſes into the <hi>glory of Kingdomes, into Lordſhip, Monarchy,</hi> and all ſuch greatneſſe: Now when it comes to the top and begins to corrupt, finds ſtormes of wrath, malice and miſchiefe, in thoſe <hi>heights</hi> it naturally <hi>returnes</hi> to its <hi>center,</hi> and <hi>retires</hi> for its own ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115670:7"/>and recover to it ſelf in the roots of the <hi>earth,</hi> the <hi>people:</hi> Hence it is that bodies politique, Kingdomes, have their ſeverall ages of childhood, youth, firme or full age, and old age as well as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of man; and one as well as the other lies under this ſentence, <hi>Duſt thou art, and to duſt thou ſhalt returne;</hi> at beſt they are but the <hi>people</hi> dreſd or ſet out with ſome outward honour, and therefore they muſt returne to mingle themſelves with <hi>duſt of common men.</hi> Againe,</p>
            <p>We know, <hi>honor eſt in honorante,</hi> honour is in him that honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, its ſeate and ſubject is in him that gives it, and therefore in the people, who doe by their <hi>breath create</hi> any man honourable or great; and their <hi>breath is the life</hi> of all greatneſſe and honour, it being but an empty Idol, a dead image, if not quickened by the affections of the people: Tis they indeed, or God ordering their ſpirits, that make men honourable; if they give him not <hi>reſpect, meanes, tribute, honour,</hi> their greatneſſe <hi>dies at heart,</hi> and becomes a heavy burden and a curſe; and therefore tis very naturall for it to come downe to its owne originall from whence it came, and doth by that recover it ſelfe; for as the <hi>people</hi> receive it into them, ſo they will quickly ſend it forth againe with greater power, and with encreaſe.</p>
            <p>This courſe of things hath its method from the minde and will of God, who hath ſaid, <hi>He will ſet over it the baſeſt of men, Dan.</hi> 4. <hi>He raiſeth the poore out of the duſt and lifteth the needy out of the dunghill: That he may ſet him with Princes of his people, Pſal.</hi> 113. The Lord hath ſaid he will <hi>exalt ſome</hi> and <hi>pull downe others; Scatter the proud in the imagination of their hearts, put downe the mighty from their ſeats and exalt them of low degree, Luk.</hi> 1. Tis a great ſport and pleaſure the Lord takes to <hi>ſet up</hi> and <hi>pull downe,</hi> to bring great things to nothing, and to exalt nothing to be all things; its excellent juſtice <hi>to poure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon Princes, to tread upon them as morter,</hi> to bring them under as the <hi>baſeſt, vileſt</hi> creatures, and to poure riches, honour and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe upon meane and baſe men, is as excellent love and goodneſſe. This he hath ſaid he will doe, and this he doth doe, and tis his prerogative.</p>
            <p>This too is taken out of a higher copy, the way of the Son of God, who is in the <hi>form of God,</hi> in the <hi>higheſt heaven,</hi> and from thence deſcends into a low <hi>ſtate</hi> of a <hi>ſervant,</hi> to be borne of <hi>a woman,</hi> to be <hi>a carpenters Son,</hi> to be with <hi>people of no account;</hi> to deſcend into <hi>the lower parts of the earth, to make his grave with the wicked, to deſcend into</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115670:7"/>hell, and from thence <hi>to aſcend</hi> againe <hi>far above all heavens.</hi> Tis the great God the king of kings, looks down amongſt men <hi>of low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree,</hi> and is content to have <hi>his foundation in the duſt,</hi> and ſo ariſe that he might <hi>fill all things</hi> and take up the <hi>loweſt</hi> into the <hi>higheſt,</hi> and be the <hi>higheſt</hi> in the <hi>loweſt,</hi> and ſo <hi>comprehend all things</hi> in <hi>one glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> that he might fil <hi>lowneſſe</hi> with <hi>majeſty,</hi> and <hi>majeſty</hi> with <hi>lowneſſe,</hi> that ther might be a perfect agreement tween the greateſt God, and the poreſt man.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee the ſecond thing manifeſted; That this paſſing of power from the Parliament, or any higher or Politique body in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lower, or naturall of the <hi>People;</hi> is rationall, orderly, and and according to the <hi>originall rule</hi> and <hi>meaſure</hi> of all things which is the minde and way of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the people ſo rais'd and cal'd up, are the ſupreme po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer or ſuperiour to all others; even to them that begat them, the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Parliament call (as is manifeſt in their <hi>Declarations</hi>) to <hi>judge;</hi> ſaying, let the <hi>People judge:</hi> they <hi>appeale</hi> to them and ſo they have ſubjected themſelves to the people: and tis but reaſon they ſhould judge; for the <hi>people</hi> themſelves, have in themſelves, the trueſt and pureſt light of judging which is reaſon; and the moſt exact ſence of their rights, and of good and evill reſpecting their liberty and ſafety: and thoſe principles in them of diſcerning men, and things relating to publique weale or woe; are more cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, more incorrupted then they are in men rais'd by them into place and office; eſpecially when all high places are poluted by the divell, and the mindes of men grow worſe by preferments and honours, as tis manifeſt they do in theſe times of defection, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſcarce any man in place, either Parliament or elſe where, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines his integrity, and the Parliament it ſelfe is one heap of ſelfe ſeeking, they being generally bias'd, both on the one ſide and the other, with places, advantages, offices, perticular intereſts, &amp; ſo not fit to be the judges of publique and common right. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tis reaſon that God ſhould call up the <hi>people,</hi> who though they be rude, deſpicable and unlearned, yet have a plain and honeſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſe in them of good and evill: and they are now ſet up to be judges of the affaires of the kingdom by God, and by the Parliament as his hand.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As they are <hi>higher</hi> being made judges and <hi>appeald unto, ſo they</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115670:8"/>are the <hi>ſtronger</hi> and more able to doe juſtice and defend themſelves then any inſtituted power: in all <hi>repreſentatives</hi> there is ſome weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe being but <hi>figurative:</hi> They are indeed very elegant, beautiful and ſtately <hi>administrations of juſtice,</hi> but have not that inward ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency and fundamental, ſtable ſtrength that is in the <hi>people:</hi> And being but formes of government, we have found them, as in this Parliament, trifling about punctilio's of honour, circumſtances and points of <hi>priviledge</hi> and <hi>prerogative,</hi> and not gone down-right to the root of the matter; which lightneſſe of ſpirit is not a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per remedy for the <hi>huge bulke</hi> of wickedneſſe that hath gotten into this Kingdom; nor able to ſtand againſt the height &amp; pride of <hi>inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> enthornd in the nation, &amp; would be a whole age &amp; more in purging out theſe evill humours in their dull, formall and cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary way of proceeding, which is wholly unſatisfactory to the juſtice of God. Yea iniquity grew upon them, and appeard in ſuch an overflowing malignity, and in perſons of ſuch eminency, that they feard to meddle with it, or feard they ſhould be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up with it, and therefore ſought the <hi>people</hi> to ſtand up and doe that which they could not; whoſe weight and ſtrength is only able to caſt out the wicked ſpirit that had univerſally poſſeſd it ſelfe of all parts of the Kingdome, eſpecially the ſuperiour parts: And the <hi>people</hi> thus authorizd and empowerd by the ſword, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with wrath and zeale againſt their adverſaries, have with much difficulty along while conteſted with theſe evils, and at laſt got the better of them, which would have long agoe (as tis moſt evident) have ſwallowed up the Parliament; and by this tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent this of the people is the ſtronger power.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There is a third conſideration proper for this, which is the power that is committed to the people; its the power of the ſword, and that in a military way: If I give a man my ſword I make him my Lord, and give him my life: ſo did the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt in committing the ſword to the people, ſubmitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to them; And with it they have declared, <hi>that they would live and dye with thoſe</hi> they have ſo entruſted: Tis as much as to ſay, we give our <hi>lives</hi> to your command; our <hi>proſperity</hi> and <hi>being</hi> is onely in you, we muſt <hi>live</hi> only upon you: Now tis reaſon that thoſe that give life ſhould give lawes too; and them upon whom we depend for our being, we muſt depend upon them likewiſe for out rule: ſo that the Parliament have made the Army the Lords protectours of themſelves, and of the right and intereſt of <hi>England;</hi> which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115670:8"/>while it ſtands, is the chiefe power: What makes a publique per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon above a private, but that he hath the civill ſword in his hand to adminiſter juſtice? Now the military ſword is ſharper, its a truſt more abſolute and independent, more exerciſd by will, and leſſe ſubject ſo the formes of law; and therefore they that have it are much more Lords over thoſe that are ſubject to it, and ſo the Army more ſuperiour to the Parliament then they to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>This I know will ſeeme ſtrange to many, and is not cleare to the Army it ſelfe, that the Parliament ſhould become a ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and inferiour, and they a higher and ſupreme power. But God hath made it ſo, and that (as you ſee) according to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and actions of men; And let men conſider but the actings of Parliament and Army, they ſhall finde the ſame thing expreſſed in deeds; which is a ſenſible and experimentall diſcovery of truth. Since theſe warres we know the maine buſineſſe of the Parliament hath beene to ſerve the Army, to gather, borrow and aſſeſſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies for them, and to provide them neceſſaries; ſome things of government have paſſed from them, but in a low, weake, in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable way; and in them they have beene up and down, high and low, this way and that way, as they received impreſſion from the Army. Its true, this hath not been ſpoken expreſly, but implicitly and darkely it hath, and the Parliament have felt it really: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt be content to beare this yoke: You have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to acquit your ſelves of it, but cannot: You have already loſt your authority, when you turnd <hi>England</hi> into a camp, and ſet up martiall power: when God leades them to <hi>reſtore</hi> it, as he did you to <hi>give</hi> it, you ſhall have it, and not till then.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This Army are truly the <hi>people of England,</hi> and have the nature and power of the <hi>whole</hi> in them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are of a popular <hi>ſtature,</hi> men of the common and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary rank of people, moſt of them of <hi>trades</hi> and <hi>husbandry,</hi> (with a ſmall mixture of the <hi>Gentry</hi>) which are the body and ſtrength of the Kingdome, and in whom the common intereſt moſt lies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are the heart and life of the people, men in whom ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares ſtrong and lively affections for publique good, manifeſted in their great labours, and hazarding their lives ſo often for the Kingdome; by which they have merited the honour to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115670:9"/>the very breaſt and ſtrength of <hi>England,</hi> and to have in them the ſoule and life of the nation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They did accept the appeale of the Parliament, and anſwer their call of <hi>the people to judge,</hi> and accepting of it, its reaſon they ſhould have it; if others either are ſenſeleſſe and cannot judge, or ſluggiſh and cowardly and will not through feare adventure; or entangled with principles of ſlavery, or engaged by particular and ſelf-reſpects to a malignant party, and ſo oppoſe them; yet they ſeeing and apprehending the danger of the Common-wealth, hearing the call of the Parliament, and being <hi>valiant for the truth,</hi> to ſteppe up upon this throne of judicature offered to them, they are unqueſtionably to be entitled <hi>the people of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. To this may be added the concurrence of the affections, prayers, councels, pens and purſes of the honeſt ſpirits in the Kingdome, who have at ſome time or other ſeald to them, and contributed their beſt helpe to them: Although it may be ſince, many through darkneſſe, weakneſſe, temptations, diviſions, petty and inferiour factions, have been diſtaſted at them, and withdrawn themſelves from them: But theſe earthly and carnall diſtractions ariſing, partly from the Armies miſcarriages and weakneſſe, partly from others paſſions, cannot obliterate and blot out the many ſubſcriptions of their names in heaven to and for the Army in their prayers and ſpeakings, eſpecially in their diſtreſſe: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe miſts are blowne away, God will leade people backe to their owne hearty and earneſt deſires of a bleſſing upon the Army, as on thoſe in whom their lives and the life and ſafety of religion and liberty lay, which are enrolled in heaven; and ſo ſhew them, though they are divided below, they are one in the higheſt, beſt, and moſt generall actings of their ſpirits.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This Army in their generall carriage <hi>towards the people,</hi> have by their tenderneſſe of them, care of preſerving them, forbearing to plunder and ſpoile them, though abſolutely in their power, have ſhewd that they have a publique ſpirit, and that the peace and good of the nation lives in them: And although they be not ſo abſolute and perfect in this, but that there be ſome ſad examples of violence and wrong, by many ill members amongſt them, yet they have generally, through the excellency of comand, and the good ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God guiding of them, ſo behaved themſelves, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple every where have witneſſed their great approbation of them,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115670:9"/>as ſaviours or preſervers of them, by joy in their preſence and teares at their departure: Tis true, the Army hath of late for their iniquities, by the judgement of God upon their miſcarriage, layne under the curſe of many people, and under a blacke and thicke cloud of wrath: But former kindneſſe will be remembred, and God will give them greater honour and acceptance, and let us know they are our ſelves, and as we have ſaid, <hi>the people of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> having publique ſpirits, and minding the good of every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in <hi>England</hi> as their owne.</p>
            <p>So that they are rightly and truly <hi>the people,</hi> not in a <hi>groſſe heape,</hi> or in a <hi>heavy, dull body,</hi> but in a <hi>ſelected, choice way:</hi> They are the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>virtue, ſpirit</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> gatherd up into <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>union,</hi> and ſo moſt able and fit for the worke they have in hand: The people, in groſſe, being a monſter, an unweildy, rude bulke of no uſe; but here they are gathered together into one pure, excellent life, and ſo uſefull and active for their good and ſafety. The cleare under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of this will be a great meanes to compoſe the diſ-affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of people to them, and to draw their hearts to them in love, being <hi>themſelves</hi> formd by God into this body, and that now their intereſt lies as truly in the Army, as ever it did in King or Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and will too be a guide to leade the Army into waies of common good, and will enlarge their principles to a generall love of all, and a deſire of making all happy as themſelves.</p>
            <p>The Fifth and laſt particular is very conſiderable, and is that which the evill ſpirit of darkneſſe hath obſcured from the Army and the Kingdome, and by it denied them the comfort and us the benefit of their being; and that is this.</p>
            <p>That the Army are the <hi>People</hi> gathered and united into a moſt <hi>excellent</hi> and <hi>divine forme:</hi> Or an Army is a ſingular Ordinance of God appointed for ſpeciall <hi>purpoſes,</hi> and at this time raiſd by God as moſt fit for thoſe noble, honourable and difficult works he hath now in hand.</p>
            <p>For the clearing of this I would have conſidered; That Army is a peculiar Ordinance of God wherein he hath a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all delight, and appropriates it to himſelfe as a power that hath more neare relation to him, and more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115670:10"/>dependance upon him, &amp; in which he will moſt viſibly ſhew himſelf, &amp; therfore chuſes ſo often to be cald the LORD OF HOASTS. And though they have a very dark and black out-ſide, being the inſtruments of his wrath, ſo they have a very ſweet and precious in-ſide, when God brings forth his owne name upon them, and diſcover them to be his: As the blackeſt afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have in them the choiceſt mercies; the croſſe of Chriſt hath glory in it; and <hi>privation</hi> it ſelfe obtaines the honour to be a <hi>cauſe,</hi> and to bring in new and more excellent formes: ſo an Army that in the outſide ſounds dread and terrour, yet hath riches treaſured up in it; which when we ſee, we ſhall not fly from it, but rejoice to have it neare us, and to goe into it for ſubſiſtence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When God brought forth the firſt creation he caſt them into this mould, an Army, and ſo laid the foundation of all his works in the camp, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.1. <hi>When he had finiſhed the heaven and the earth, and all the hoſt of them:</hi> In this poſture hath he put all things, not onely the ſtars above, <hi>who fight in their order,</hi> march in their courſe, but the very <hi>locuſts goe forth by bands.</hi> The reaſon is, that they might all quietly ſerve him under the protection of an Army; and that if they be infeſted with any adverſe power, they might have force to retreat to: In this military wiſedome hath <hi>the Lord of Hoaſts made and eſtabliſhed the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. When God expreſſes his preſence with his people in the world, he manifeſts himſelfe to be in a military ſtate, <hi>I will encamp about my houſe: Pitch his tents about them;</hi> ſo in a ſecond, middle or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall ſtate he is an Army, while he preſerves us he gathers his <hi>Miniſters</hi> about us in a body, an Army.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When he comes in his laſt and great <hi>glory,</hi> he brings his <hi>hoaſts with him,</hi> and comes as a Generall and <hi>Lord of Hoaſts, thouſands of thouſands</hi> attending upon him, all <hi>his Saints and Angels;</hi> ſo that wherever the Lord appeares, it is in this ſtate, either in the reare or loweſt, in the body or midſt, in the van or higheſt, tis in this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; the creatures a <hi>camp,</hi> the Church militant a <hi>camp,</hi> the Saints in glory a <hi>camp</hi> or <hi>hoſt</hi> likewiſe.</p>
            <p>In the providence of God in the world, God hath made great uſe of Armies.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They have beene the parents of all the Empires and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the world; all the preſent Common-wealths upon earth muſt owne the ſword to be their originall, and confeſſe that from it they had their beginnings; and tis rationall, for an Army hath
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115670:10"/>in it all government, and all parts of government, order, juſtice, &amp;c. in higheſt and nobleſt virtue and majeſty.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As all Kingdomes come out of an Army, ſo are much cheriſhed and upheld by the ſame; moſt Kingdomes flouriſhing while their military virtues are kept bright and cleare by uſe; and quickly languiſh when the ſword is wholly laid aſide; The preſence of the ſword keeping off deſtruction from them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As Kingdomes are begotten and nouriſhed by Armies, ſo doe they againe reſolve into them as into their firſt principles: And when by ſtrength of wickedneſſe civill ſocieties are diſturbd, they naturally retire to a military, as unto their owne Father, for ſafety; for they have a peculiar <hi>majeſty, ſeverity, activity</hi> and maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line vertue or force to uphold a ſtate againſt ſuch evils as are in the world, which no power beſides hath: And therefore Armies are not ſuch hideous evils, as ſome imagine, but are beautifull, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and exceeding profitable ſocieties; not onely ſcourges, but ſaviours and protectors; they have motherly bowels as well as iron hands: and ſo in Gods raiſing and ſupporting this Army there is a moſt perfect wiſedome of God; caſting his people into this form is very ſeaſonable and proper for us at this time.</p>
            <p>For we are at this time become a wilderneſſe, the pale of civill power being broken down, and men let looſe to furious and beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſts, ſuch as would leade them to inhume and brutill villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, were there not this curb in their mouths; nor could any man promiſe <hi>himſelf</hi> ſecurity in what he hath, but that God is a wall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us in this Army: And wiſe men wil eaſily ſee, if ſenſe of ſome preſent <hi>ſuffering,</hi> or adhering to another ſide or party did not blind them, that the violent and exorbitant luſts of men in this age, is no way to be reſtrained but by this ſharpe bit, an Army: Tis true, tis our wickedneſſe hath brought us to it; but ſeeing it is ſo, tis mercy in God to put himſelfe and people into ſuch a poſture for our defence: And this is the minde of God1 formerly decal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not onely to <hi>breake nations,</hi> but to <hi>rule them alſo with an iron ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The worke that God hath now in hand is not an earthy, fixt thing, but he is upon <hi>motion, marching</hi> of us out of <hi>Egyptian</hi> dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and bondage, into a <hi>Canaan</hi> of reſt and happineſſe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tis proper for him to gird up himſelfe, to contract himſelfe from a vaſt body of a Kingdome into a narrower compaſſe, into a few ſpirits in an active body, ſuch as an Army is, looſe and free
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115670:11"/>from the clogge of old formes and cuſtomes, to act lively his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and to follow him into thoſe new waies and pathes of truth and liberty, that he ſhall lead them: and becauſe this work is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended upon with difficulties, and through a wilderneſſe full of wild beaſts and enemies on all ſides, its his great wiſedom to <hi>Arme</hi> himſelfe and to imploy men skilfull at the <hi>ſword</hi> as well as at the <hi>truel,</hi> to build Jeruſalem with <hi>weapons</hi> in their hands, our great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers requiring it. And we know the beginings of God's great works of good to his people, have been by Armies: as their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babilon,</hi> in the ſame part doth he walk ſtill, and therefore doth he now in his laſt appearing gather <hi>his hoaſt</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, and put us into this ſtate as he hath foretold, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. <hi>The camp of the Saints, The Armies in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have we brought you forth as the <hi>Virgin daughter of Zion,</hi> a ſelect and <hi>choſen Generation,</hi> a lovely and pretious people: But yet a femall, a woman, and ſo in fleſh and weakneſſe being ſubject to ſin and ſuffering: a ſtate that muſt be tried, and by temptations im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved: tis no ſure nor ſtable condition, being not in compleat and eternall union with God: you have had the <hi>love of eſpouſals,</hi> many kinde favours from God, a Father, a Lord: but have ſind againſt them and him, for which he hath caus'd you a while to wander in darke and troubleſome waies, and not admitted you to that ſtate of reſt and glory which he intends to you. He hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Diadem</hi> from off your head, for your unbeliefe and departure from him, and for that impurity which was in you: he ſtript you of your beautifull garments of <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> that once clothed you, and ſo expos'd you to <hi>wrath, curſes, reproach,</hi> and put you again into a <hi>new fire of trouble</hi> to purifie you, to make you <hi>ſeeke the Lord.</hi> But he <hi>hath not dealt with you, as he hath dealt with other people: he hath refrained for his nameſake,</hi> that he might not <hi>make an ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of you.</hi> Becauſe he will have a people that <hi>ſhall bear his name. Hath he ſmiteen him as he ſmote thoſe that ſmote him? Or is he ſlain accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſlaughter of them that are flaine by him? No, In meaſlure when it ſhouteth forth thou wilt debate with it, be ſtayeth his rough winde in the day of the eaſt winde. By this therefore ſhall the iniquity of Jacob be purged, and this is all the fruit to take away his ſin. When he maketh all the ſtones of the alter, as chalke ſtones that are beat aſunder, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 27, There is a <hi>a ſhouting forth of the righteous branch</hi> in you, and therefore we muſt <hi>ſtay all rough windes,</hi> and breath gentle gales upon you: your <hi>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity being taken away,</hi> we will <hi>preſent</hi> you holy to the Lord, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115670:11"/>marry you to the God of your ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Know therefore, that the <hi>Lord,</hi> the <hi>most high God</hi> is in the <hi>midſt</hi> of you, is <hi>in you</hi> and <hi>with you</hi> in <hi>a glorious preſence,</hi> as you have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed: The <hi>glorious God,</hi> or <hi>the glory of God,</hi> dwels with you, or God in <hi>his higheſt glory</hi> reſts upon you; ſo that you are not only <hi>the People of England,</hi> but <hi>the People of God,</hi> ſanctified by the holy, mighty, wiſe <hi>ſpirit of God,</hi> and en lowed by the <hi>divine</hi> wiſedome, ſtrength and juſtice; and you are as an Army, ſo the LORDS <hi>hoaſt;</hi> or the Lord himſelfe in his <hi>great majeſty</hi> appearing amongſt men in an hoaſt; the whole hoaſt of heavenly and bleſſed <hi>men</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> with all their various and innumerable excellencies and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons gathered together, and embodied upon the earth in you. An earthly Army in union with the <hi>heavenly hoſt,</hi> or <hi>the Lord of hoasts</hi> in Mount <hi>Sion</hi> among his people <hi>gloriouſly:</hi> This is your <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> the <hi>Lord Jehovah</hi> is your <hi>covering,</hi> your <hi>garment of ſalvation,</hi> and onely this can juſtifie you; honeſt intentions aid good meanings are <hi>rotten rags,</hi> and <hi>too narrow</hi> to cover your <hi>nakedneſſe;</hi> we ſhall therefore open and unfold this glory unto you, and bring forth this your righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Lord is with you in his higheſt and greateſt <hi>majeſty,</hi> there is no power, no glory of God, but tis in you and with you, and no power nor glory greater then that which dwels in you, none beſides, none above, none beyond it: The Lord is here, the <hi>most high God,</hi> and with him all <hi>power in heaven and earth;</hi> there is no wiſedome or ſtrength that you have not, and all imaginations of a power abſent from you either <hi>in heaven or earth,</hi> is an injury or accuſation to Gad and to you, <hi>is theft and robbery,</hi> ſtealing away the riches of God from <hi>you</hi> and from <hi>himſelfe in you;</hi> if you look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Kingdome of God, the new creation, new heavens, and new earth, as abſent or to come, you deny the <hi>holy one with you,</hi> who is preſent in deed and power, though under your weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Lord is with you in perfect union and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; you are what he is, he is what you are; whatever is in him tis communicated to you, and whatever is in you, is communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him: Is there power or glory in God? tis in you alſo: Or is there weakneſſe in you? it lies upon him: Or is there righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in God? tis in you as it is in him, to live in it, act in it and by it; to employ and bring forth: And is there infirmity in you? tis in him as tis in you, a clogge, a burden, an enemy hated,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115670:12"/>ſeparated, taken away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nothing now is ſpoken of God, but may be ſpoken of you; you being in union with him: or nothing ſpoken or done to you, but tis done to God with you, you being one: And tis the blaſphemy of hell and divell to ſeparate God from you, or you from God. Will men ſay you are Rebels, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers; they ſay it of the Lord: or will you, or ſatan in you, ſay you are weake, and men, and can't do ſuch high things: they are too great for us, you and they will know you ſpeak the ſame of God, and ſo judge him as weak and unable to do them. For in nothing you muſt be divided: or if you think that is God's, but this is our work, you wrong God, and your ſelves: you muſt ſpeak the <hi>words</hi> and doe the <hi>workes</hi> of God: God is now, God in the earth, and you an <hi>Army in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lord is with you <hi>in ſpirit and truth,</hi> eternally, inſeparably, in a <hi>kingdome that never ſhall be deſtroyed:</hi> in an <hi>everlaſting covenant that cannot be broken.</hi> The kingdome is ſo with you the Lords people, as it ſhall <hi>never be taken front you;</hi> but ſhall endure for ever, and all oppreſſing feares or dark doubts, they are of the malicious one, your enemy, and the darkneſſe of hell that <hi>obſcures the glory of God,</hi> which is an everlaſting light, a Sun that will not ſet: and all attempts of Satan or his inſtruments, will be as waves againſt a rock daſh'd in pieces, and you ſhall grow from <hi>a little ſtone, to a great mountain:</hi> from <hi>a little branch, to a great tree,</hi> that ſhall ſpread it ſelfe <hi>and fill the earth with fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this mountain ſhall the <hi>hand of the Lord reſt.</hi> Having laid this foundation; <hi>now ſhall thy light break forth as the morning, and thine health ſhall ſpring forth ſpeedily, and thy righteouſneſſe ſhall go before thee, and the glory of the Lord ſhall be thy rerc-ward:</hi> you ſhall at once have <hi>light,</hi> cleare light to walke by, <hi>health</hi> to cure your diſeaſes, to make you ſtrong: and <hi>Righteoueſse</hi> to juſtifie all that you doe: For theſe cannot be ſeparated when the <hi>Sun riſes,</hi> with light to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect he is a <hi>Sun of righteouſneſſe;</hi> to juſtifie and take away ſin and ſhame, and hath <hi>healing in his wings,</hi> gives life and ſtrength to doe what he leades us to do.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Seeing the Lord hath paſſed from other powers to you, and exalted or ſet up you as the preſent ſtanding power of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and hath given himſelfe to you, and taken you up into his <hi>glorious preſence;</hi> then muſt you <hi>exalt the Lord, publiſh, declare the name of the Lord.</hi> Confeſſe him to be in the mid'ſt of you: ſound
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115670:12"/>him forth <hi>evidently, boldly, aloud;</hi> ſay the LORD lives with you, that <hi>he is come to reigne amongſt you gloriouſly.</hi> Bring him forth in brightneſſe and power: let this <hi>oppreſſed one go free;</hi> tell it to all the nations, the <hi>Saviour of Iſrael is come</hi> to redeem his people from all their enemies: you doe mutter it, and ſpeak it ſoftly, and by halves, but <hi>declare it</hi> fully, that we may heare the <hi>ſhout of a King in the camp,</hi> that <hi>God himſelfe is in you of a truth:</hi> Let us heare the ſound of that Trumpet in the Camp, which the <hi>ſeventh,</hi> laſt and bleſſed <hi>Angel ſounds;</hi> And thoſe <hi>great voices in heaven, ſaying, The Kingdomes of this world are become the Kingdomes of the Lord and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall reigne for ever and ever:</hi> Doe you, not in <hi>words</hi> but in <hi>power</hi> and <hi>truth, caſt your crownes down to the earth, fall with your faces to the earth;</hi> your <hi>crowne</hi> of ſucceſſes, victories, lay them downe in the <hi>dirt,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but earthly; and your faces, your excellency of honeſty, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, wiſedome, honour, <hi>lay it down to the earth,</hi> for tis but <hi>duſt;</hi> and doe <hi>you worſhip God, live God, confeſſe God, exalt God,</hi> his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and power which is <hi>worthy, perfect, almighty;</hi> Say (and doe) <hi>we give thee thanks, O Lord God almighty, which art, and waſt, and art to come, becauſe thou haſt taken to thee thy great power, and haſt reigned, Rev.</hi> 11. Give tip your ſelves from humane, weake and fleſhly ſtate, as thanks or a free will offering, to the <hi>glory</hi> and majeſty of <hi>God,</hi> to act and live the <hi>life of the Almighty,</hi> put on the Almightineſſe of God, be cloathed with God Almighty; and know the Lord <hi>is</hi> with you <hi>who art,</hi> deny not his <hi>preſent</hi> being in power and glory in you, and confeſſe he alwaies hath beene with you; <hi>which waſt, and that which is to come,</hi> that which is eternall and everlaſting, is <hi>preſent;</hi> disjoine not theſe, let not him that is now with you, be another from him who is to come, or from him who was; but ſay and <hi>ſweare in truth,</hi> that he <hi>who is to come,</hi> in all that he will doe, is now preſent with you to doe it; <hi>He hath taken his great power and hath reigned;</hi> he hath already begun, hath taken his <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>great power,</hi> and is in the exerciſe of it.</p>
            <p>Therefore, <hi>Ariſe and ſhine forth, for thy light is come, and the glory of the Lord is riſen upon thee: For behold the darkneſſe ſhall cover the earth, and groſse darkneſſe the people, but the Lord ſhall riſe upon thee, and his glory ſhall be ſeene upon thee; And the Gentiles ſhall come to thy light, and Kings to the brightneſſe of thy riſing.</hi> This lifting up the name of the LORD in you will have a very great effect upon others and your ſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Upon others; Sad darkneſſe now covers the <hi>People</hi> of this
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115670:13"/>Nation, &amp; they are in perplexity, not knowing which way to go: Do you ſhake your ſelvs from the duſt of your own vileneſſe, and put on the goodneſſe, power and wiſedome of God, and all people will <hi>flow in</hi> unto it for helpe and ſuccour; you will preſently cauſe all to gather about you for reliefe: The glory and light of God will melt the heart of your adverſaries into love to you; <hi>The ſons of them that afflicted thee ſhall come bending into thee, and all they that deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee ſhall bow themſelves downe at the ſoles of thy feet, and call thee the City of the Lord, the Sion of the holy One of Iſrael:</hi> Holding forth the goodneſſe of God you will be <hi>a joy of many generations;</hi> revive the Nation now lying in a grave of miſery: And thoſe that continue obſtinate, the name of the Lord will be a terrour to them, fill their faces with ſhame and confuſion; 'Twill be as lightning, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly blaſting and withering them; 'Twill pierce through their heads, hearts and loynes, and for ever diſable them from any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings or practiſes againſt you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For your ſelves; This preſence of God will burne up all thoſe low and baſe ſpirits that are amongſt you, covetouſneſſe, pride, ſelf-love, ſhall not dare to abide in the camp: 'Twill be an anointing to you, filling you with royall and Princely minds, create majeſty, power, wiſedome, juſtice and truth amongſt you; fill you with light and underſtanding, ſo that all your wayes ſhall be clear and plain before you, and every one ſhall be more mighty then a hundred, able to fill the earth with righteouſneſſe and truth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You being the People of <hi>England,</hi> and all power and dominion deſcending and coming downe into you: You are the <hi>Mother</hi> of the Nation the earth, baſis and foundation upon which all lie: and being thus, in the light and ſtrength of <hi>God,</hi> you are <hi>Jeruſalem which is above, the Mother of us all:</hi> And therefore muſt,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Spread your armes to receive the whole Nation, open your boſomes to us, and let us ſee that you carry in you all the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and welfare of the Kingdome; manifeſt the largeneſſe and comprehenſion of your ſpirits, that you have in you the <hi>King</hi> and his royalty, the <hi>Parliament</hi> and their wiſedome and majeſty; theſe two <hi>in Treaty</hi> nay <hi>in perfect union,</hi> that religion, trade, juſtice, order, covenant, ſettlement, reformation, riches, honors, propriety lies treaſured up in your breaſts: What you have not, <hi>gather into you all the offices, treaſure; authorities, ſeales, judicatures,</hi> all the prerogatives and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115670:13"/>priviledges of the Nation, let nothing lie out of you and be loſt, but be you the center of all, and call in all into you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let it appeare that they are in you <hi>as in the Lord; In the Lord in you,</hi> and ſo are in you moſt excellently, ſafely; that though we have them not in a viſible and ſenſible way, yet let all know they are in you as corne ſowd in the earth; that you do embrace them all in your tendereſt bowels of love and care, and but entruſted for a time with them; that as all have ſeene a <hi>ſeeds time, a fall of the fruit</hi> and <hi>leafe,</hi> ſo we may expect a <hi>ſpring;</hi> as we have ſeene a <hi>death</hi> by you of all, ſo we may hope to ſee a <hi>reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Receive them and retaine them all in judgement, make a thorow digeſtion of the good and evill of them all; keepe them as in a fire, by the ſword of divine juſtice, with the exactneſſe of God; cut off all evil things and perſons, ſeparate the <hi>precious from the vile</hi> in the Common-wealth, &amp; let nothing that is of particular, or hurtfull intereſts remaine, but be a mercileſſe grave to all ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, oppreſſion, to all ungodlineſſe and unrighteouſneſſe; let all things that are juſt, good, holy and honourable, incorporate with you, receive a new life from you: Know the <hi>Lord</hi> is upon his <hi>Throne</hi> amongſt you, and every one, and every thing that is not his muſt be rejected; <hi>Every plant that he hath not planted muſt be pulled up;</hi> there muſt be no judge but the Lord; and no rule of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting or refuſing, but the divine law of the <hi>ſpirit of God:</hi> What God will owne and ſay, <hi>tis mine,</hi> ſhall live, and what he will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime, muſt dye, and the poore, narrow minds and fancies of men muſt not be enthroned, nor have leave to judge amongſt you.</p>
            <p n="4">4. So receive and retaine them as ready to reſtore them when they are tried and purified; let it appeare that you are the womb of the Kingdome, that will with labour and travell conceive, breed and nouriſh it: But that it is to you a burden, and when the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>time</hi> comes, you cannot but deſire to be delivered of it; and that it is your ſorrow to have it in you, and will be your joy to bring it forth unto others. By letting forth this publique and good ſpirit you will be carried up above that petty, low ſpirit of malice or enmity to any; you will kill and tread upon this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, which is a baſe principle and unworthy of God, and would keepe you downe in earthy and darke wayes; but coming forth into the largeneſſe of God, you will act in high, noble and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous waies.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115670:14"/>
            <p>And by being thus enlarged you will be as the wals of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, incloſe and imbrace all men, and all intereſts, and of a ſudden gather up all men into your ſelves, ſurpriſe and catch mens hearts before they are aware: and begirt the Kingdom with your arms, and binde up all her breaches in union with your ſelves: and be a preſent eaſe and ſtay to mens ſad and aking ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits: that whereas they are now in a wilderneſſe and know not where they are, they may of a ſudden, their eies being open'd ſee they are in the hands of a wiſe and good God, taking care of them by his own people whom he hath bleſſed with largeneſſe, judgement and goodneſſe for their ſafety. That men may ſee that though they are fallen, yet not into a pit of utter deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or not into the hands of enemies, but unexpectedly upon a very good bottome; a people having the tenderneſſe and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Nation, and the firmneſſe, largeneſſe, judgement and ſtability of God in them, both in civil and ſpiritual things: and diſcover a foundation, a firm rock and beginning of peace and happineſſe to the Kingdome ariſing up in the midſt of us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let me bring you forth too as the higheſt and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt power in the Nation, being ſuperiour to King, Parliament and All, in a true and good ſenſe: Tis God and Nature gives it you, and you wrong the Kingdome and your ſelves, till you come forth in a clear and free owning of it: You darkly and in the twilight ſteal it by your actions, but deny to profeſſe it, which ſubjects you to reproach and ſcorn as adultereſſes and thieves, if you could boldly and in the light and ſtrength of God challenge it as your right and manifeſt it; what is now fear'd would be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced: Truths while they are faintly own'd and by halves are abuſed and rejected: when they lie low in the duſt and are obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by darkneſſe are terrible, and men flie from them: but when we lift them up into our faces, and give them a throne in our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and free poſſeſſion of them they are lovely and acceptable; and command ſubjection in all: Beſides the Kingdome is unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and looks this way and that way for a head: ſome look to the King, and others to the Parliament, and neither appears to head them, which keeps them ſtill in a wavering ſtate, farre from any ſtaiedneſſe or ſetledneſſe: Now lift up <hi>your heads, be upright:</hi> ſtand up in the <hi>name and power of God,</hi> and this will compoſe the divided and doubting mindes of men, knowing where to fix, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115670:14"/>attract and ingage all to you: for you appearing their natural and head cant be diſown'd.</p>
            <p>Tis true you may be thought a <hi>Jacob</hi> a ſupplanter of your elder brother of his birth-right: But you having the bleſſing too, it will bear you out: God gives it: <hi>The ſmell of my ſonne is as the ſmell of a field which the Lord bath bleſſed. God give thee the dew of heaven, and the fatneſſe of the earth, and plenty of corn and wine. Let people ſerve thee and nations bowe down to thee: Be Lord over thy brethren, and curſed be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that curſeth thee, and bleſſed be he that bleſſeth thee.</hi> Shew forth that riches of <hi>heaven,</hi> that light and glory of God, and that <hi>fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the earthy,</hi> that goodneſſ, power, juſtice and kindeneſſe that is in you, and then all power muſt bowe to you, all will ſeek to you.</p>
            <p>While you hold it forth in a night dream, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> doth his brothers <hi>ſheaves bowing to his:</hi> they deſpiſe and envie you for it, but ſhew your ſelves poſſeſt of all the <hi>corn of Aegypt,</hi> of all the <hi>good of the land,</hi> and then your brethren there being a <hi>famine in the land</hi> of peace and righteouſneſſe, they will be glad of you, and come and remove all their <hi>ſubſtance</hi> to you, into the Camp, to be <hi>preſerv'd</hi> and <hi>kept alive</hi> by that ſtore at health and ſalvation that is in the preſence and goodneſſe of God laid up amongſt you and in you.</p>
            <p>Your halting in this point is very diſhonourable and unſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, to write your ſelves the <hi>ſervants</hi> of the Parliament, and yet to exerciſe power over them: And it puts you upon groſſe and unſeemly actions: to patch and bodge, to pick out and cull ſome from the Parliament that goe againſt you, and leave others that are as unfit to govern as they you refuſe, only becauſe they vote with you: This hath great appearance of ſiding and partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: it were more juſtifiable farre to diſſolve the whole and ſtand upon your own abſolute and ſupreme power: For while you goe as a <hi>Snail</hi> with that old <hi>houſe upon your heads,</hi> you will never make any diſpatch in your buſineſſe, they being in that ſtate in which you own them, an emptie vain idol of no uſe at all, but will be a clog to you perpetually, and make you formall, low, ſervile, and tedious in all your actions.</p>
            <p>Therefore aſcend into that height into which you are call'd, <hi>ſhake your ſelves from your duſt</hi> of formal relations to other powers that are <hi>ground to pouder by the juſtice of God,</hi> that you might come forth of them: <hi>Looſe your neeks from your b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lls,</hi> be no longer <hi>captives:</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115670:15"/>They have and God hath made you <hi>Judges,</hi> and given you author<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity and dominion: <hi>The mountain of the LORDS houſe, ſhall be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in the top of the mountains, and ſhall be exalted above the hils, and nations ſhall flow unto it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſhall appear that you are indeed the <hi>ſupreme power</hi> taken up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>throne of God,</hi> living <hi>in the ſecret place of the moſt high.</hi> That the moſt <hi>high God</hi> rules in you, and gives his <hi>higheſt</hi> wiſdome and juſtice to you: And that you have a more exquiſite ſenſe of the good and evil of the Nation then any, and more able to judge what is <hi>truly</hi> for their <hi>good,</hi> and to reſolve thoſe queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and controverſies which yet lie in doubt and darkneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us.</p>
            <p>And that you are in the power of God <hi>mighty to ſave</hi> them when men cannot, being the <hi>people of GOD,</hi> or qualified with a divine ſtrength: Though the Kingdome be miſerably broken, and thoſe that have attempted to heal it through unskilfulneſſe and unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifulneſſe have more abus'd the poor people: yet <hi>there is hope in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael concerning this thing. There is balm in Gilead:</hi> Though there be none in the waies of men, yet there is amongſt the <hi>people of God in Iſrael, that is a prince with God, and prevails over men:</hi> Though the <hi>Sunne be turn'd into darkneſſe, and the Moon to blond:</hi> there is confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhame and deſpair, in and upon the greateſt lights of the world: <hi>Yet in mount Zion and in Jeruſalem ſhall be deliverance, as the LORD hath ſaid, and in the remnant whom the LORD ſhall call,</hi> Joel 2.31, 32, <hi>in the LORDS people, a deſpis'd remnant is</hi> Englands <hi>ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore let them know, that though through the floud of wickedneſſe that is broken forth amongſt us, religion be laid waſte, order and government in Church and Common-wealth be diſſolved, and the honour, royalty, greatneſſe, riches, trade of the Nation be viſibly loſt, yet there is a power with you that can recover all theſe into light and health againe, to the ſatisfaction of all that <hi>deſire to ſee good daies:</hi> This al-creating, al-reſtoring power is with us, and wil not faile us in our worke: <hi>Iſay.</hi> 58.11, 12. <hi>The Lord ſhall guide thee continually, &amp;c. Thou ſhalt be like a watered gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and like a ſpring of water whoſe waters faile not: Thou ſhalt build the old waſte places, thou ſhalt raiſe up the foundations of many generations, and thou ſhalt be called the repairer of the breach, the reſtorer of paths to dwell in:</hi> There is a fountain and <hi>ſpring</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit of God</hi> that ſhall run over the whole Kingdome, and not <hi>faile</hi> in any worke you are upon, be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115670:15"/>it never ſo high, great and honourable, and all that is excellent in the Kingdome, though it be ſunke into the foundations, yet you wil <hi>restore</hi> and <hi>repaire</hi> them again.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I preſent you to the Kingdome, and ſo muſt you preſent your ſelves to them as the fruit of their own <hi>womb.</hi> The ſon of God begotten by the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> of this Nation, form'd and ſhaped by the divine wiſdome out of the bowels of the people: <hi>Or that little ſtone, a precious ſtone,</hi> being irradiated with the holy and divine nature, <hi>cut out of the mountain</hi> or the Kingdome <hi>without hands:</hi> There is in you the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the Kingdome: the vigour and ſtrength of the Nation: her firſt-born you are: the ſtaffe and ſtrength of her age, and although <hi>of all the children that ſhe hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly brought forth</hi> by her elections, laws, cuſtomes; there is none that can <hi>take her by the hand,</hi> and <hi>guide her</hi> out of her diſtreſſe, yet you will kindely put under your ſhoulders to carry her in your <hi>arms</hi> to a place of reſt.</p>
            <p>Caſt away therefore that vail of a party of any particular inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and looke forth in your owne true face a <hi>childe</hi> and <hi>heir</hi> of the Kingdome, our owne fleſh and bloud, of tender affection to us, and pity of us; we have given you lite and being by our purſes, prayers, perſons, councels; tis our life, religion, eſtate, cauſe, bloud that runs in your veines, and therefore you owe to us your ſelves, life, ſtrength, paines, labours, watchings, and ought to lay them all out freely for us, purely in love, and repayment of the debt you owe to us; And coming upon theſe terms as the childe of our travels, pangs and diſtreſſes, the childe of our deſires and prayers, the iſſue of many conſultations, affections, disburſments, feares, hopes, the firſt borne of our owne <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Husband, God,</hi> and bearing his owne image upon you, holineſſe, righteouſneſſe, goodneſſe; we cannot but with joy embrace you after our ſore travels and afflictions; and though many people dying in feare and deſpaire, as <hi>Rachel,</hi> call you <hi>BEN-ONI, The Son of my ſorrow,</hi> yet your Father who lives will call you <hi>BENJAMIN, the Son of my right hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the Spirit of the Lord file off your roughneſſe and un-even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and blow away that duſt that covers your beauty, and we ſhal ſee you a ſtone ſolid, firme and ſtable, that cannot be broken by any devices or force; a precious ſtone, that contains in it all the intereſts, all that's good or worthy in the Kingdome; That you are as <hi>cut out, ſo laid</hi> by the hand and art of God <hi>in Sion; a tried ſtone,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115670:16"/>a precious corner ſtone, a ſure foundation, he that believeth maketh not haſte;</hi> You have <hi>beene tried</hi> and are <hi>found precious,</hi> and a <hi>corner ſtone</hi> in which all our rights are laid, and ſo ſquar'd by God with that exact ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, as to be a rule and ſquare to the whole Kingdome, and <hi>a ſure foundation of an everlaſting peace,</hi> ſuch a foundation as hath the whole building in it; and this will make men ſtay upon you and believe in you, not <hi>haſtening</hi> after any other helpe or Saviour.</p>
            <p>You are, being formed by God, of that true and intrinſecall worth, that you have the <hi>priſe</hi> of the Nation in you, and that in <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and ſo in the pureſt and beſt <hi>union,</hi> which is to us a ground and bottome of <hi>true peace:</hi> But you neglect this true, ſubſtantiall <hi>union,</hi> and are making another, <hi>an agreement of the people,</hi> which ſhewes a groſſeneſſe and filthineſſe of ſpirit; not able to diſcerne the <hi>union</hi> of God in you in <hi>one heart</hi> and <hi>minde,</hi> and not onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt your ſelves, but of the <hi>whole Kingdom</hi> in their true and right ſenſe, and therefore are framing a carnall and fleſhly one, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cuſtome of the Heathen; a worke below the Lord, and a, deſcending into the earth to doe that which God hath done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready moſt excellently: You are a living <hi>Altar,</hi> and <hi>a lifting up a toole unto it doth polute it:</hi> The Lord is building <hi>a houſe which is from heaven,</hi> and you know <hi>the patterne is in the Mount,</hi> and is thence brought forth; the <hi>stone it made ready,</hi> and there muſt <hi>not be beard while tis building, neither hammer, ax, or any toole of iron in the houſe;</hi> this <hi>ſawing</hi> and <hi>cutting</hi> to make an outward; literall agreement, vexes and wounds your ſpirits, and tends to <hi>diſ-unite</hi> you from the Lord, and from each other: The Lord is with you in <hi>union,</hi> he is <hi>one,</hi> and gives you true <hi>unity</hi> one ſoule and ſpirit: Therefore ſtand up and come forth in that entire forme that the Lord hath caſt you into, in that image that he ſtamps upon you; a <hi>living ſtone</hi> in all parts, as <hi>poliſhed</hi> ſo <hi>quickened</hi> by the ſpirit of God.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Let me preſent you and bring you forth as the <hi>Lords hoaſt</hi> in the great majeſty of an Army; in this moſt excellent forme in whom the Lord is as <hi>a mighty man of warre,</hi> cloathed with <hi>zeale as with a garment;</hi> ſtript out of ordinary, common and cold formes of government, and <hi>making bare his arme</hi> in the moſt terrible and maſculine conſtitution of an <hi>Amy; Glorious in his apparell, travelling in the greatneſſe of his ſtrength, red in his apparell, and his garments like him that treadeth in the wine fat; for the day of vengeance is in my heart, and the yeare of my redeemed is come: A DAY of vengeance,</hi> this worke muſt <hi>be cut ſhort in Righteouſneſſe,</hi> quicke and ſpeedy, and that too in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115670:16"/>perfect union with <hi>ſalvation</hi> or <hi>redemption,</hi> which muſt be long, A YEARE, it muſt laſt for ever, <hi>The yeare of my redeemed it come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In this reſpect you muſt appear moſt abſolute in your comands, ſtrong, mighty and indiſputable in your authority; ſuch is the government of an Army, and tis proper in the worke you are in: <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.35. <hi>And he doth according to his will in the Army in heaven, and among the inhabitants of the earth, and none can ſtay his hand, or ſay unto him, what doſt thou? An Army in heaven,</hi> that's your place, ſtanding in <hi>God,</hi> and inſpired by the <hi>Spirit of God;</hi> one with the <hi>heavenly hoaſt,</hi> majeſty or abſoluteneſſe, is but due here, and that without danger, when the Wiſe God guides your reſolves; for nothing muſt come forth but that which hath the face of God upon it, and that in which divine juſtice and goodneſſe doth appeare: Being the Lord doth it, <hi>who can ſay, What d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt thou?</hi> This excellency of God and all other glorious perfections are amongſt us, and muſt no longer be buried under humane weakneſſe, and the ſtaggering blindneſſe and uncertainty of the creature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You muſt appeare in greater terrour to evill doers, then any power before you; with your ſword <hi>whetted, furbuſh'd, bathed in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> made bright and glittering with the Spirit of God; That it may aw &amp; dazle the eies of the Nation into a fear of tranſgreſſing: Former <hi>ſwords</hi> have beene too dull to cut up iniquity; wickednes hath ſleighted and ſcorn'd them, therefore muſt you appeare in greater ſeverity, every act and word of juſtice piercing to the heart; <hi>ſearching 'tweene the ſoule and ſpirit, 'tweene the bone and marrow;</hi> to kill wickedneſſe in the <hi>root</hi> of it; to deſtroy not onely the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward acts of injuſtice and oppreſſion, as contrary to our ſenſible and outward peace, but their inward ſtrength, as contrary to the glory and goodneſſe of God: Not onely ſtrike at humane miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages, which are weake, but at thoſe Diabolicall wickedneſſes that are ſtrong, and the Father of theſe inferiour oppreſſions; which you are able to doe, having a <hi>ſword bath'd in heaven,</hi> and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutting the divine juſtice; and by doing this you ſhall ſecure the things you doe, and for ever diſable Satan to bring forth any more miſchiefes upon us.</p>
            <p>This is that you have harped at, the fulfilling of that promiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.6, <hi>amp;c. The high praiſe of God in their mouth;</hi> This is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to have <hi>God</hi> in our <hi>mouth,</hi> and God in his praiſe, in his glory; yea, his <hi>high praiſe</hi> to ſpeake forth the higheſt honour of God, his higheſt, laſt and utmoſt holineſſe and juſtice. <hi>And a two edged ſword
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115670:17"/>in their hand,</hi> one of <hi>fleſh,</hi> another of <hi>ſpirit:</hi> to cut up <hi>ſinners</hi> with the one, and <hi>ſinne it ſelf</hi> with the other: The firſt is common to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Heathen; the ſecond, the peculiar honour of Chriſt, who hath before us'd it in his <hi>mouth,</hi> but now in his hand, hath <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, preached it,</hi> will now <hi>act</hi> it in <hi>deeds,</hi> and ſo bring forth the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> ſword of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>outward</hi> of the <hi>fleſh</hi> to be adminiſtred together by one <hi>hand:</hi> And by this ſhal you not only ſlay wicked men, but wicked works, or wicked things. To deſtroy or cut off evil men only is Heatheniſh, to deſtroy wicked workes onely, and not men, is Chriſtian: to cut off both together is the laſt great and perfect judgement of the world: by this you ſhal doe that which hath been fore-told, in <hi>Daniel</hi> 9.24. <hi>To finiſh tranſgreſſion, and to make an end of ſinnes, and to bring in everlaſting righteouſneſſe:</hi> ſo to break the <hi>ſtaffe of oppreſſion, that the rod of the wicked ſhould no longer lie upon the lot of the righteous:</hi> or to deſtroy the <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> out of the earth <hi>root</hi> and <hi>branch,</hi> that there may no more come out of their loins: that ſinne may be barren and childeleſſe: this is the <hi>ſecure condition</hi> you aim at, and that which is promis'd, and wil be made good to you: To ſet up ſuch true and bright laws, ſo holy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, in ſuch power and efficacie, as no ungodlineſſe ſhal be able to paſſe thorow them, or ſtand in the ſight of them: Such a majeſty of the face of God will bring forth it ſelf, as <hi>will behold no iniquity:</hi> ſinne ſhall not abide in mens actions, no nor hearts, nay not in the firſt father of it, Satan, but in al it ſhal be utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd: This is not beyond the power of the <hi>Lord of hoaſts with us,</hi> but that which is our portion and prerogative: and muſt be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. To ſet up the <hi>new Jeruſalem</hi> in ſuch brightneſſe and everlaſting purity, as no unclean thing ſhall come into it: nothing defile it.</p>
            <p>As you ſhall come forth in <hi>flames of fire</hi> againſt all the workers of iniquitie, ſo that not one ſhal eſcape: ſo in <hi>walls of fire</hi> towards all that is <hi>good,</hi> to defend and ſave it: We have that one <hi>law-giver that can kill and make alive,</hi> that can ſave as <hi>well as deſtroy: preſerve gold</hi> as wel as <hi>conſume droſſe:</hi> be <hi>a Saviour of life unto life, as well as death unto death:</hi> to bring all the good of the earth into the good of heaven, as wel as to caſt the evil of the world into hel: to <hi>looſe</hi> the <hi>holy One</hi> out of his <hi>bonds,</hi> as wel as to <hi>binde</hi> the <hi>wicked one</hi> in his: Tis a black and foul work to kil only, and not to reſtore: but this is our chiefeſt excellency: to ſave what is good in al, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to bring it forth in a holy and perfect way: to beget <hi>children that ſhall be princes in al the earth.</hi> Or by the Spirit of God to beget Principalities &amp; powers, Kings, Lords, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of our own <hi>righteous</hi> and <hi>juſt</hi> nature, and of greater
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115670:17"/>vigour and power of righteouſnes and wiſdom, then our ſelves in our own perſons: we are able in our God to ſtamp the divine image upon men, to form them into the likeneſſe of God, to convey our own ſpirits with our authority, to impower with ſpirit as well as office, and if we cant do that we can do nothing in <hi>truth,</hi> nothing <hi>in God,</hi> nothing different from the moſt common and ordinary Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens: and but that which will deſtroy us as ſoon as we have made it. If we ſet up an earthly and fleſhly form, it will corrupt and turn enemy to us that exalt it, except we ſet up <hi>God,</hi> and ſet up <hi>in all</hi> the powder of God, and <hi>all</hi> in the power of God, or all quickned with the Spirit of God: And being <hi>the hoaſt of God,</hi> and having all fulnes of the Spirit, or being attended with al the <hi>divine perfections,</hi> we can and ſhall ſpread forth in the <hi>fruits of righteouſnes:</hi> And eſtabliſh righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes in perſons and things, living righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>This is your true ſtate, and the firſt and leaſt of it: and leſſe then this is not your righteouſnes: I cant ſpeak or think leſſe of you: &amp; he that thinks or ſpeaks leſs then this or contrary to this, be it Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan in you or others, <hi>blaſphemes the tabernacle of God, &amp; them that dwel in heaven:</hi> This is your own life, and all below it are <hi>fancies, dreams</hi> and <hi>lies: Babylon</hi> and confuſion keeping &amp; holding <hi>Zion</hi> from her glory.</p>
            <p>Tis a bleſſed face of God, and the light of his countenance ſhining upon you; and I know there is another face which is the ſame in you that <hi>anſwers</hi> to this, and though it hath bin vaild awhile, the brightnes and power of this will ſcatter that miſt and call forth its own ſelf and likenes in you to imbrace this: <hi>Righteouſnes looks down from heaven</hi> here upon you: we might queſtion whether it would be received, or no, whether it would not be judged a fancy, a conceit, but that we know alſo, <hi>Truth ſprings out of the earth,</hi> the ſame ſpirit hath been acting a long while in you, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and in the earth buried under fleſh, but now wil come forth and anſwer to this, or ſay, tis <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th,</hi> and make it <hi>truth</hi> in the performance: You wil not ſay this is <hi>righteous</hi> in God, he may do al this it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for him, but not for us: No, <hi>righteouſnes and peace have kiſſed each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> you are r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>conciled to this <hi>righteouſnes, the partition wall is broken down, of two made one new man:</hi> and ſo you cannot but receive and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in it: <hi>mercy</hi> here <hi>meets</hi> with <hi>truth</hi> in your breſts: <hi>The heavens powr down righteouſnes, and the earth opens, and ſalvation ſprings forth together.</hi> The Lord is come down, yea the heavens, all the <hi>hoſt</hi> of them, al the <hi>ſtars</hi> of <hi>righteouſnes,</hi> and the <hi>ſame truth</hi> ariſes out of you and theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, are <hi>ſalvation.</hi> God out of you works but in <hi>weaknes,</hi> in <hi>trouble:</hi> ſo do you out of God; both together bring forth <hi>ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115670:18"/>
            <p>I ſhall I know meet with this objection from your ſelves and others, that this will be true, but not yet; and that it is farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe with you for the preſent; tis that you expect, but tis not yet manifeſted.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, That this truth is eternall, and there is no moment wherein you can ſay tis not, tis he that <hi>was, is and is to come:</hi> That therefore it is darknes that denies it; or that's a deepe pit that ſaies tis not here: doe not abide in ſuch darkneſſe of hel where eternall truth will not be admitted: That as it alwayes hath been ſo it now is brought forth borne into the world: <hi>the childe is born</hi> I have been long travelling for him, and now lay him amongſt you: it is true it is in the Stable amongſt beaſts, <hi>Swadled and lying in a Manger,</hi> in a very meane and contemptible condition, but I ſhall own him and nurſe him, and ſo will you I hope, it is your <hi>own God and Saviour,</hi> though wrapped up in fleſh, and in the midſt of a beaſtly crue, yet ſmiling in your face, offered to you, yea ariſing up in you; And he <hi>whom you have ſought for is now come into his Temple;</hi> you have long conceiv'd him, and <hi>travelled</hi> too to bring him forth; and now <hi>Behold thy King cometh riding upon an aſſe;</hi> receive him and ſay, <hi>This is the Lord, we have waited for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you can yet ſay, theſe things are brought forth in <hi>you,</hi> but not in us, we cannot owne them in power, <hi>you</hi> may, we are yet in the fleſh; tis your light, not ours; we live not in this glory, nor can act in it, we muſt goe our way.</p>
            <p>No, tis yours as well as <hi>mine,</hi> and not <hi>mine</hi> as diſtinct from you, but <hi>mine in you</hi> and <hi>with you;</hi> for we have but <hi>one life, one ſpirit,</hi> and if it breake forth firſt in me, tis for <hi>your ſakes:</hi> Tis not a perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall or private ſpirit, but the Spirit of God and of all the Saints; tis the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>ſoule</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> and therefore you cannot be ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to it; ſure ſo ſoone as you ſee it you will ſay, this is <hi>our por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> our rock, our ſtrength.</p>
            <p>But if you are in the fleſh, and this glory be not ſuffered to act in you, What's the reaſon of it? <hi>Who lets?</hi> Is it not the man of ſin? If it be ſo, then you confeſſe your ſelves guilty of what I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly written; for this man of ſinne is not a limb or member, but a compleat man, and ſo hath all ſinne in him: where fleſh is it is a <hi>body of ſinne,</hi> having all <hi>iniquity</hi> weav'd together into one vail; pride, hypocriſy, ſelf-ſeeking, enmity againſt God, and all in the higheſt way of ſinne, <hi>whoſe coming it after the working of Satan, with all power, and ſignes, and lying wonders, and with all deceivableneſſe of unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115670:18"/>Tis no leſſe then <hi>Satan,</hi> though <hi>with all power and ſignes</hi> of praying, ſeeking God, juſtice; <hi>and lying wonders,</hi> wonderfull great things, but lying, becauſe ſeparated from the eternall truth: <hi>with all deceivableneſſe of unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> I know none <hi>righteous</hi> but God, and all waies beſide are to deceive: And if this ſpirit be in you, it is not <hi>idle,</hi> it comes forth; this bloud runs in the veines of al your actions; the Lord ſaid it of you long ago, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 21.24. <hi>Yee have made your iniquity to be remembred, in that your tranſgreſſions are diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo that in all your doings your ſins doe appeare</hi> — <hi>And thou prophane, wicked Prince of Iſrael, whoſe day is come when iniquity ſhall have an end:</hi> This filth lies not ſtill, but comes forth in all your actions, and fils them with darkneſſe, weakneſſe, confuſion, inſtability: but an <hi>end it come</hi> of ſinne, and that wicked Prince is caſt out; <hi>I am pacified towards you, fury is not in me,</hi> I have no more to accuſe you of.</p>
            <p>If you now object, as I doubt you will, your being in the fleſh, your weakneſſe, inability to manage theſe high and great waies, the ſenſe of your unworthineſſe and ſinfulneſſe obſcuring this glory: Obſerve this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You now are the accuſers; I have done, I have nothing to ſay againſt you; I appear'd <hi>in fury and jealouſie againſt you,</hi> and by that fire have purified you, and burnt up that droſſe that was in you; its all caſt into the <hi>bottome of the ſea, I remember it no more;</hi> its under my feet, I am above it; and now I am juſtifying, and you are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing your ſelves, and this ſhall be our controverſy hereafter, I ſhall offend you by declaring a Righteouſneſſe in you which you you may ſay is too high, too great, and you be your owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demners; or being reconciled, and eſtabliſhing a Covenant of peace, you will then be aſhamed of all the evill that you have done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Know your ſinnes lie upon the Lord, they are his, he beares them all; there is <hi>none</hi> now under iniquity but Chriſt; you are Righteous, the Lord is your Righteouſneſſe; there is <hi>a fountaine opened for ſin and for uncleanneſſe to waſh in; That fire of jealouſie</hi> in which the Lord appeared in my laſt, hath judged and deſtroyed the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked one, and now appeares your righteouſneſſe. That was an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment of the <hi>filthy Prince,</hi> this is a clearing of the <hi>holy One,</hi> and both in the <hi>power and truth of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The conſideration of your unworthineſſe, unfitneſſe may be to you ſad and troubleſome, it is to me glorious; It being the great deſigne of God to viſit his people in a low condition, <hi>in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115670:19"/>in Babylon,</hi> and to glorifie himſelfe and the riches of his power and mercy, to love freely, to cover and take away iniquity, to <hi>blot</hi> them out as a <hi>thick Cloud;</hi> God now hath taken your filthy gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from you, and cloathed you <hi>with beautifull garments,</hi> and put <hi>a crowne upon your heads; He gives you beauty for aſhes:</hi> You were burnt to aſhes by the wrath of God, here's now beauty for you: You are brought forth in your full proportion your <hi>originall,</hi> your feet, your firſt ſtanding and your head, the glory of the Lord in eternal praiſe.</p>
            <p>The holy God takes pleaſure to raiſe the higheſt buildings out of the loweſt and pooreſt beginnings; the more glorious the end, the viler and deeper the foundation; God that raiſed the firſt creation out of a Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>os, and <hi>eſtabliſhed it upon the waters,</hi> will raiſe the <hi>new heavens and new earth</hi> out of a weake and confuſed heape of waters, a poore and deſpiſed people; And there where men look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not for him will he appeare: Out of <hi>Nazareth</hi> from whence no <hi>good comes; from Egypt,</hi> a place of thraldome and captivity; <hi>And thou Bethlehem, little among the thouſands of Judah, out of thee ſhall he come forth unto me to be Ruler in Iſrael: This man ſhall be our peace when the Aſſyrian is in the land; And the remnant of Jacob ſhall be among the Gentiles, in the midſt of many people, as a Lion among the beaſts, Mic.</hi> 5. All which ſhews, that the Lord chuſes to manifeſt himſelfe firſt in thoſe that are beaſtly, gentle, ignorant, meane, deſpiſed people, and even then when the <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> the <hi>man of ſinne is in the land,</hi> in them and upon them.</p>
            <p>The Lord hath been with you informer mercies, and in late ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; he appeared amongſt you in a ſpring of bleſſings, ſince hath lyen downe in diſgrace; made <hi>his grave with the wicked, and with the rich in his death, he hath beene numbred with tranſgreſſours:</hi> Your ſins have ſlain your <hi>Lord,</hi> your <hi>glory,</hi> and your <hi>Lord</hi> by <hi>death</hi> hath borne and <hi>ſlaine your ſins;</hi> you have <hi>lien dead,</hi> becauſe Chriſt your life hath beene <hi>kild</hi> your ſins; but Chriſt hath <hi>died</hi> with you, in you, into you, and <hi>Sampſon-like,</hi> by his <hi>death</hi> hath kild all <hi>his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;</hi> your tranſgreſſions have made <hi>his grave,</hi> &amp; there buried them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and looſe their deſtroying nature in him, hanging upon him; he how <hi>offers up his ſoule a ſacrifice for ſinne,</hi> which is an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and pleaſant thing to God, who is pleaſed to ſee our ſins fall by Chriſts death; and ſmelſ <hi>a ſweet ſavour</hi> in that death that takes away the miſery and griefe of his people, and out of which <hi>he riſes</hi> with them to glory and righteouſneſſe: Now ſhall <hi>he ſee of the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115670:19"/>of his ſoule and be ſatisfied, and by his knowledge ſhall my righteous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant juſtifie many;</hi> he had not beene righteous if he had not died; but dying under our ſins, he and we riſing together are both righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: It <hi>ſatisfies</hi> the Lord to <hi>travail</hi> with you, to <hi>travail</hi> out of your grave, to be in death with you, and thence to aſcend to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and it matters not if men be unſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Be you unrighteous in your ſelves, the Lord coming forth out of this obſcurity, and ſhining upon you, you will ſay, <hi>Surely in the Lord have I righteouſneſſe and ſtrength, even to him ſhall men come, and all that are incenſed againſt him ſhall be aſhamed; In the Lord ſhall all the ſeed of Iſrael be juſtified, &amp; ſhall glory:</hi> Confeſſe the Lord amongſt you, 'twil <hi>juſtifie</hi> you and <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> you; and then they that are incenſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you are <hi>incenſed</hi> againſt him; uncover his face clearly, and all will be aſhamed to oppoſe their Lord, and ſo you may goe on in righteouſneſſe and ſtrength, glorying.</p>
            <p>Your way hath beene darke and obſcure to your ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; here is light for you, ſhewing you whence you come, and whither you goe, <hi>Mentioning you from the womb, declaring your genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which hath beene cut off,</hi> and ſhewing your end, or that <hi>Canaan</hi> that you are going too; The Lord is here a <hi>Sun and ſhield,</hi> no good thing will he with-hold; a plain path of juſtice, mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe trodden out to you, ſhewing what you muſt doe, whith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r you muſt goe, and what guide you have to direct you: That you are now the mother and womb of the Kingdome into which all is caſt; and the Father of mercies ſaies you are the Father too, and muſt bring it forth in perfect and eternall righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>I have no more to ſay; or rather I will ever ſay, and ſay more ſtrongly and plainly what I have here ſpoken weakly and darkly; <hi>Behold the Lord hath proclaimed unto the end of the world; Say you to the Daughter of Sion, Behold thy ſalvation cometh; behold his reward is with him, and his work is before him; And they ſhal cal them the holy people, the redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Lord! And thou ſhalt be called, ſought out a City not forſaken;</hi> Tis your <hi>ſalvation</hi> that is <hi>come,</hi> you <hi>ſhall ſee evill no more;</hi> let all the world know it, let the news of it fill the dark and troubled earth, <hi>proclaim</hi> it openly, he gives you a <hi>reward</hi> of all your paines and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, he brings al good with him; you will need no ſupplyes but what he will daily bring forth to you: <hi>And his worke is before him;</hi> Tis now cleare what he will doe, <hi>reigne</hi> over the Nations in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe; ſet up an <hi>everlaſting Kingdome</hi> for the Saints that ſhall never be deſtroyed: And all muſt owne you and confeſſe you to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115670:20"/>be the holy people; <hi>holineſſe</hi> that hath beene the worlds <hi>ſcorn,</hi> will now be their <hi>ſaviour;</hi> that which they have <hi>derided</hi> ſhall they now <hi>truſt</hi> in, your juſtice and faithfulneſſe; you are holy with the <hi>holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God,</hi> or <hi>holy as your heavenly Father is holy, to raine downe bleſſings upon the juſt and unjuſt,</hi> and to let the <hi>Sun</hi> of favour and ſalvation to ſhine generally upon all, upon the evill and the good: God hath <hi>ſought you</hi> out wandring in a wilderneſſe, and not knowing whether to goe; and manifeſted but are not <hi>forſaken,</hi> not left to your own waies, wils or councels, but taken into <hi>neareſt union</hi> with the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, wiſedome and glory of God; though for a <hi>little moment</hi> he left you, <hi>with everlaſting kindneſſe hath he gathered you,</hi> and will not forſake you any more.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:115670:20"/>
            <head>The Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>GOD hath divided the judgements of men in theſe times, and concerning the Army, at this time very much: giving to ſeverall men particular prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and theſe with a <hi>perverſe ſpirit</hi> engaged in enmity one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſome ſo fierce againſt them as they can hear no good of them: ſome ſo blinded with ſelſe-love to their party, fooliſh flatterers can ſee no ill in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to theſe halfe-headed men, poor ſhreds of Chriſtians, I ſhall ſeem to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict my ſelfe in theſe two pieces I have writ; and it may be offend both: I confeſſe it hath been my portion to have <hi>all men offended at me,</hi> and can beare it; but I am willing now, if a little reaſon will ſatisfie to remove the offence, if not, I muſt waite.</p>
            <p>When this little booke <hi>man</hi> comes to be open'd and interpreted by the large Spirit of God; we ſhall finde its a <hi>womb</hi> that hath <hi>two Nations in it,</hi> that it contains in it all <hi>the depths of Satan,</hi> &amp; all the <hi>treaſures of wiſdom:</hi> When God comes to ſearch and judge men, there are <hi>Goats</hi> and <hi>Sheep cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> and <hi>bleſſed</hi> in every one; and they are pitifully blinded and narrow ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits that ſee not all evil, all evil in particular as well as in generall, all in higheſt and intenſe degrees in themſelves: and you muſt ſee this or elſe you cant ſee the higheſt and chiefeſt good in your ſelves. The Lord ſaith to <hi>Peter,</hi> Math. <hi>16.17. Bleſſed art thou Bariona,</hi> and ver. <hi>23. Get thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde me Satan:</hi> And amongſt the Prophets it was very common, as in <hi>Ezek.</hi> to declare againſt the wickedneſſe of <hi>Iſrael, as worſe then Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria or Sodome,</hi> and immediatly to declare them the <hi>Lords People, his own flock, in covenant with him, &amp;c. Hoſea</hi> in the ſame place ſaies, <hi>ye are not my People,</hi> and again, <hi>ye are the People of the living God:</hi> now adultereſſes, then married; yet no contradiction: no more then the <hi>evening</hi> and the <hi>morning to be one day;</hi> or fleſh and <hi>ſpirit</hi> to be in one heart, or the <hi>man of ſin to be in the Temple of God, and to be exalted there above him;</hi> or Gods own people in Babylon: This is not strange to me. Nor to declare the evil of the Army, as in the fleſh, and much good in the ſame Army, as they are in God.</p>
            <p>Nor do I count it inſtability to <hi>condemn the wicked one</hi> in men, and <hi>juſtifie the righteous:</hi> When I ſee <hi>Iſrael in their bloud</hi> to turn my face from them, and ſeeing them <hi>Iſrael</hi> to turne <hi>my face</hi> towards them: or to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate
<pb facs="tcp:115670:21"/>the <hi>precious</hi> from the <hi>vile;</hi> to handle a <hi>two edged ſword,</hi> to <hi>kill</hi> and <hi>ſave,</hi> or to <hi>ſave</hi> with <hi>vengeance:</hi> let it be counted lightneſſe, I chuſe to be a <hi>fan</hi> to ſeparate the <hi>chaffe</hi> from the <hi>wheat,</hi> and be fire to burn up the <hi>droſſe,</hi> and <hi>purify the Gold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To you that are againſt the Army, this is no wrong to you, to manifeſt <hi>God here,</hi> and in him ſalvation <hi>to all</hi> his own and to <hi>all that is good:</hi> we are broken in pieces miſerably, and if the Lord will heal us, let us not ſtand upon circumſtances, whether it be by friend or foe, higher or lower, if it be <hi>peace and righteouſneſſe.</hi> If God appear in a <hi>Jew,</hi> though <hi>we are ten men of ſeveral languages, lets all take hold of his skirt, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we will goe with you, for we have heard God with you.</hi> This be aſſur'd tis God that is here ſet up a generall and univerſall good, and Saviour, and be not afraid of him, though he comes to you in the appearance of men below or againſt you.</p>
            <p>To the Army and your party, I ſay, The love here ſhew'd you is true <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:</hi> which <hi>vaunteth not it ſelf, is not puffed up, ſeeketh not her own, but beareth all things,</hi> &amp;c. This love bumbles you to be under all, and to beare the burdens of all: inlarges you to imbrace and comprehend all, ſtrengthens you to ſave and deliver all: It doth not cover your evil, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move it that it might be no hinderance to your doing good.</p>
            <p>Tis in my eye and heart to advance th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> true and publick good, THE LORD, and not any party of men. And in this I ſhall not fail, for God will be, muſt be exalted: And therefore I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. S.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:115670:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
